Okay, good morning church. Great to see all of you here today. Hope it's fun just sharing some of those
oldest memories that you have. Great way to connect with one another. If we haven't met yet,
my name is Pete. I'm one of the pastors here at HMCC and it's my joy to share God's word with you
this morning. If you want, you can open up your Bibles to Ephesians chapter 1. That's what we're
going to be looking at today. And as you get started, I also just want to personally welcome
any of you who are new today. If you'd like to just say hi, get to know each other after the
celebration, I'd love to meet with you and just hear your story, hear what God's doing in your
life and welcome you to our church family as well. Also, we just know a lot of people are
checking out different churches, different ministries around campus and around Ann Arbor
right now. That's awesome. Glad you're here today. And whether you make this your church
home or not, we're happy to be able to worship with you and definitely encourage checking out
other campus ministries and other churches around the area. God's doing a lot of great
things around here. But as we get into today, hopefully this will be helpful to you and even
seeing if this is a church family, church home that you would like to be part of. As we get into
today's message. I think this is actually a really important Sunday for our church to gather
and worship and hopefully hear from the Lord today. Over the past couple of weeks, we've been
focusing on some really foundational things for our church community. We've been talking about
our mission, which is to transform lost people into Christ's disciples who will then transform
the world. That's rooted in the Great Commission in Matthew 28. And last Sunday, we talked about
our vision to become a transcultural spiritual family, reaching our neighbors, the nations,
and the next generation. We saw a picture of that in Acts chapter 13. And as we've been talking about
those things, that all kind of is leading into today. Hopefully you'll see some connections
because today is our theme Sunday where we're talking about kind of an annual theme that we do
each year to just kind of put some focus and direction on how we're going to seek God together,
how we're going to pray and pursue a deeper relationship with the Lord as we go through
the coming year. So I'm going to be sharing that with us here this morning and hopefully that'll
really help us to get off this new season of ministry on the right foot. So as we get into
that today as a way of kind of getting us thinking about it a little bit. I've always been fascinated
by the way that different movies actually speak to our kind of human condition and desires and
the things that we pursue in life. And if it's okay, I'd like to share a couple examples of that
with you, maybe to meet some different generations here, because we got some younger people, we got
some little bit older people, and we got some kind of older people in this room here today. So
we got to kind of hit the spread. And maybe if I could start, maybe some of the oldest of us here
in this room, Gen X and a little bit beyond, you might remember a story that started a long time
ago in a galaxy far, far away, right? If you were, I mean, not too many of us were alive back in 1977
when the original Star Wars Episode IV, A New Hope, came out. But when that came out, and some
of you just watched it later, like myself, I'm an 80s kid. When you watch that, you see young Luke
Skywalker, right? And he is stuck on a desert planet doing chores on his uncle's farm, and he is
frustrated. He is complaining that he can't go hang out with his friends, and he can't go to the city
to buy power converters. And he's just, you can tell he's like full of teen angst, and he is just
upset with where his life is at, and longing for something more, something bigger, all right? And
then he meets Obi-Wan Kenobi, right? And from Obi-Wan, he discovers that he is meant to become
a Jedi Knight, and ultimately, that he is going to be the one who will bring down the Galactic
empire, right? So we see that story play out. Now, if you're just a little bit younger than that,
maybe some of our millennials here in this room, well, you might have grown up watching
Thomas Anderson, Mr. Anderson, right? Growing up and working a soul-crushing cubicle job
at a software company in the Matrix, right? Constantly being berated by his middle managers
for minor infractions, just living out a menial daily existence. You can put that up. That's okay.
go ahead. So this is in the Matrix, right? And Neo's there. We come to know Mr. Anderson,
Thomas Anderson, as Neo. And as we get to know him, we find him then meeting Morpheus, right?
And Morpheus lets him know that actually he, that his, oh goodness, Morpheus reveals that his entire
life is actually an illusion, meant to keep him oblivious to the reality of the Matrix that he's
living in, right? And that Neo is actually called to be the one who will liberate humanity. So this,
again, it's like, okay, starting from this menial existence, now realizing a bigger purpose. And
lastly, for those younger folks here, Gen Z, Gen Alpha, those kind of folks we have in the room,
it's probably most of us here at this point, maybe you're a little bit more familiar with Mirabel
Madrigal, right, from Encanto. She's the only child in an extraordinary family born with a magical
gift. And so she goes through her days singing and dancing, right? But while her sisters move
mountains and sprout blossoms on command and do all these magical things, Mirabel's daily life
consists of being pushed out of the way, setting the dinner table, and pretending she isn't crushed
by feeling ordinary and overlooked and forgotten about. So she goes through that. But then when
cracks begin fracturing the foundation of the family home, none of the family's super-powered
members can diagnose or fix the problem, and Mirabelle discovers that her lack of a flashy
superpower is precisely what makes her capable of seeing the unspoken grief and broken relationships
threatening to destroy them. And she meets a secret family member who we don't talk about, right?
What I hope you realize, if you reflect on some of these things, is that regardless of the
generation, whether it came out a few years ago or 20 years before that or 20 years before that,
What connects all these stories is the desire to live for a greater purpose, to do something
meaningful and significant with our lives, not to settle for the menial and mundane of
the day-to-day.
And I think these movies are successful, and they gain big audiences and followings and
fandoms.
Why?
Because each of us has the same desire within ourselves.
We long for that.
We want to be part of that.
We have this innate sense that life is about something more than the narratives of our
surrounding culture, and that our daily lives do matter. The things that we do, our work, our school,
our family, our friendships, those are all valuable, but that God actually has something more for us in
and through all of that. And so all that is to lead up to just introducing our annual theme for
this year, which is the idea of higher calling, and that God is wanting us to rise above temporary
pursuits to live for God's eternal purpose. This is going to be our annual theme for this year,
higher calling. And as part of our theme for this year, we're going to be studying the book of
Ephesians together. Over the next eight months, we're going to go through the whole book together,
but we're going to start that out today, and that's going to provide some guidance and some structure
to growing into this higher calling that God has for all of us. And so I'm going to start by
reading Ephesians chapter 1, just verses 1 and 2. We're going to cover two verses today, and then
get into that and start to see what the higher calling is that God has for each one of us. So
let me start by reading Ephesians 1, 1-2 for us together. It says, Paul, an apostle of Christ
Jesus by the will of God, to the saints who are in Ephesus and are faithful in Christ Jesus,
grace to you and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ. Amen. We'll pause there,
and let me pray for us as we look into God's word here this morning. God, we invite you to come
and meet us and speak to us and guide us into this coming year ahead. We're thankful to be
together as a spiritual family of the church, and that we can grow closer to you, and we can live out
the higher calling that you have for us together. But God, we're just at the beginning of that
journey, and so we pray that you would meet us here, that you would speak to each one of us
personally, speak to us together as the family of the church, and really build us up, Lord, into
this higher calling as we start this new year ahead. Thank you, God, because your word is good
and holy and precious and true, and we want to hear from you, God, and we want to live out your
calling for us together. Thank you, God. We love you. It's in Jesus' name that we pray.
Amen. Amen. Okay, so as we get into this here today, like I said, we're just going to cover the first
couple verses, and believe it or not, there's actually more here than we're able to really cover
today. As we start looking at it, brief introduction to the letter to the Ephesians, this is a letter
that was written from Rome to Ephesus by this guy that we know as the Apostle Paul. And as we look
into this here together, I mean, just a couple of touch points. In Acts chapter 19, we find out this
is the first time that Paul actually spends time in Ephesus. So if you look, just to give us some
geographical reference points here, if you look at the map here behind me, you'll see up here
this is a map of Paul's third missionary journey. He had actually previously passed through Ephesus
on his second journey, but on this third one, we find that he now comes to this place called
Ephesus, and he spends about two and a half or three years there. It's the longest that he spent
in any place as he was traveling and doing ministry.
Where he is when he writes the letter
is actually over in Rome.
If we can go to the next one.
And Rome is way up here, right?
Capital of the Roman Empire.
So he's come a long way to get over here.
This is about six to eight years later
after Paul initially spent that time in Ephesus.
And we find that by Acts chapter 28,
he is actually imprisoned in Rome.
He is under house arrest there for about two years.
This is about from A.D. 62 to 64, and during the time that he spends there, he wrote the letter to
the Ephesians, he wrote Colossians, he wrote Philippians, he wrote Philemon, he wrote all of
these letters that are so important to our understanding of the Christian faith and to
what God was doing even in the churches at that time. And this is really significant for us as we
start to look into it here today, because as we look into this letter, it's a little bit different than
even some of Paul's other letters. Like if you read through all the letters that he wrote, you'll
see that in some other letters, Paul writes to correct serious issues of sin or false teachings
in some of these churches. So if you read like Galatians or 1 Corinthians, you'll realize, oh man,
people were like really getting the gospel wrong and misunderstanding it. Or my gosh, in Corinth,
they're doing some really wicked, sinful things in the church. It's got to be corrected. But here
when he writes to the church in Ephesus, he's writing to the church that he spent the most time
in, had the strongest relationships with, and that he'd had the time to really build it up into a
healthy, fruitful, spiritual family that is now living out their faith together. And so he now is
writing to really strengthen and build up this church in Ephesus and with gospel truth and
exhortation. That's what we're going to be finding as we look through this letter. But as we look at
the letter, we get the opportunity not just to see the teachings that Paul shares, but we also
have the opportunity, especially here today, to look at Paul as an example of what it looks like
to live out a higher calling that we're talking about this year. And so we're going to dig into
that here together, and we meet Paul as he introduces himself in this letter and describes
himself as an apostle of Christ Jesus. Now, what does that mean? We'll dig into that here for a
moment. By the way, I want to recognize that for many of us here, maybe we've grown up in church
our whole lives, and we've just kind of been familiar with some of these terms in the Bible,
or maybe we have this understanding or take it for granted even what it means to be an apostle,
stuff like that. For some of you, maybe you're really new to all of this. Maybe you're like me
and like I didn't grow up in the church and when I first came to our church, I was like, man,
what's that word mean? What's all this mean? We're going to try to just unpack it as best as we can
so all of us here can be on the same page. What we see as we get to know Paul as an apostle of
Jesus Christ, the word apostle is a Greek word apostolos and that means one who fulfills the
role of being a special messenger, ambassador, or envoy. It means somebody who is set to do a task
or accomplish a mission. And we find out as we look elsewhere in the New Testament in the Bible
that Paul isn't just generally an apostle of Christ Jesus, but he is specifically called the
apostle to the Gentiles. If you were with us last week, you know that that word Gentile,
that means anyone who wasn't a Jewish person. That's what the Jewish people called all the
other nations. If you're not Jewish, you're a Gentile. And so Paul knows his calling is to go
and make Jesus known to all the other nations surrounding that area, to every nation of the
world. He knows that that is his calling. And as we see his calling play out through the New
Testament, we're not going to go through this in fine detail, but man, this guy ended up doing a
lot. So what are some of the things he did? He preached the gospel across over 50 cities and
towns, went all over the place. He also planted at least eight churches that we have solid records
of, potentially more, but at least eight that are very clearly identified in the New Testament. He
also wrote 13 New Testament books. So, so much of what we study and read and learn about Jesus,
about the kingdom of God, all of that we learn from actually Paul's letters. As he was doing,
he wasn't only a teacher, he was also someone that really ministered in the power of God. He
healed the sick, cast out demons, raised the dead, all those things that Jesus taught all the rest of
his disciples to do. And he also then discipled the next generation of church leaders. People like
Timothy and Titus and Silas and Mark and Sosthenes and Priscilla and Aquila and Epaphras and Luke.
Many of these people that became really significant leaders in the early church were people that were
trained and equipped by Paul as he did his ministry. But we also see through all those great
things that he did, he suffered greatly for his faith in Christ. He was whipped, beaten, stoned,
imprisoned, ultimately executed in the city of Rome a few years after this letter was written. He first
went to Spain, then came back to Rome, and there was executed under the Roman Empire. As we look
at all of this and get a sense of who Paul is as this apostle of Christ Jesus, I think this is
an opportune time for us to ask the question, how did Paul become Paul? How did he discover and live
out the higher calling that God had for him? And as we look at his life and ask that question and
understand that, we can also ask ourselves, how will we become who God has called us to be? Because
God has a calling for each one of our lives. It's not going to look the same as Paul's, but he has a
unique calling for each one of us that he wants us to grow into, to discover, and then to live out
with our whole hearts. And so today we get to start that journey of understanding that. And as
we think about like, well, how did Paul become Paul? He actually answers the question for us
right away. He says, I'm an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God. He says, that's how it
happened. How did I become Paul, the apostle of Christ Jesus? It happened by the will of God.
Now, what does that mean?
What does that mean?
That could be like sort of a dismissive statement.
Oh, it's the will of God.
But no, that actually happens in some really specific ways for Paul as we explore and unpack his life.
So as we look at that, I mean, first, notice some sovereign foundations in Paul's life.
By the way, I'm borrowing that term, sovereign foundations, from an author named Robert Clinton.
And he talks about how some early life experiences can influence your future calling.
And so Paul, he has some of these sovereign foundations that God put in place in his life
that enable him to become who he ultimately was and the calling he ultimately had.
A few interesting things about Paul.
Number one, he's born to a Jewish family in the Roman city of Tarsus.
So he's born in the Roman Empire, and he was given the name Saul.
He was actually named after Israel's first king.
So his parents seem to have had high hopes for him, okay?
Like he's under some pressure, okay, from his family.
But because he's born in Tarsus, he had Roman citizenship.
He would have grown up not only learning the Hebrew language, but also the Greek language,
so he's at least bilingual, if not more.
And in Tarsus, he would have also learned things like Stoic and Epicurean philosophy
that was prevalent in that region of the Roman Empire at that time.
And he also even got to know Greek mythology.
He didn't have Percy Jackson yet, but he got his hands around it.
He understood a bit of what's going on in the Greek mythic world.
But as he grew up, we see that he also received formal Jewish education.
And so that's significant.
Like, for many of us, we take education for granted.
And for many of us, we just assume, well, of course, I'm going to go to high school.
Of course, maybe I'm going to go to college, things like that.
Back at that time, only about 1% of young Jewish men, men only, not women,
only about 1% of young men received a formal Jewish education beyond an elementary level.
For most people, by the time they were like past elementary years,
well, then they were just learning a trade,
or they were being apprenticed in a business,
or they were just joining the family business.
That's what they did, and they didn't have any further schooling beyond that.
That's what a lot of Jesus' other disciples were like.
They were like fishermen, right, doing that kind of stuff.
Paul is one of that 1%,
the people that would have gotten into the University of Michigan, right,
people that get that elite education for him that was in Jerusalem
under a teacher named Gamaliel, who taught him to be an expert in the laws of the Old Testament.
And so he's received this Jewish education, and then because of that, he was able to excel
as a Pharisee. And many of you know the Pharisees. These were people that they get a really bad rap
in the New Testament. There are a lot of conflicts with the Pharisees and Jesus. But really at their
core, these are people who are just really serious about understanding the Old Testament
scriptures, wanted to be very intentional about not violating any of those laws or commandments,
And they were so serious about this, they memorized and obeyed not only the 613 commandments
in the Jewish Old Testament, but they also, on top of that, added hundreds or thousands
of what were called fence laws that were intended to keep someone from even getting
close or having the possibility of violating one of the commandments.
So they added hundreds and thousands of commandments on top of the 613 that we see written in
the scriptures.
And Paul says, man, he excelled in all of them.
He was really good at this stuff.
Not just knowing it, but living it, obeying it.
That was his life.
And so as he excelled as a Pharisee,
well, a result of that is he then ended up
persecuting the church.
He says, hey, there's some new teaching going on here.
People are talking about this rabbi Jesus,
and people are saying some things about him
that I don't think are true, I don't think are good.
He's leading people astray,
and so he's persecuting the church.
He's so serious and zealous about his faith.
And so as we look at all of this, I mean, like Paul, Saul, he had the best education.
He had career success.
He had the admiration of others.
He had the best passport to travel the world and go wherever he wanted to.
But ultimately, he finds out that all of these are temporary pursuits.
These are what the author of Ecclesiastes might have called chasing after the wind.
It doesn't really go anywhere, right?
And when does he discover this?
When does he understand this?
Is it in the classroom as he's just kind of going about his day,
teaching his own students?
Is it as he takes a special seminar about something about the real meaning of life?
No, it's as he meets a person.
We find out that ultimately, after all those sovereign foundations,
he then encountered Christ on the road to Damascus.
If you haven't read that, I would encourage you,
go read Acts 9, 1-9.
He encounters Jesus on the road to Damascus,
and there he finds out
that what all of these followers of the way,
these Christians, what they've been talking about,
that this rabbi died on the cross and rose again,
that he did this to forgive people of their sins,
to give them eternal life,
this message he's been hearing and rejecting,
he finds out that it's real, that it's true,
that this is where you actually find eternal life.
And as he has this encounter with Jesus,
it's fascinating.
It completely changes the direction of his life.
And I think it's interesting to note
that this is when he's about 30 years old.
Paul would have been born slightly after Jesus.
He's about 30 years old at this time.
That's fascinating
because most of Jesus' earlier followers were teenagers.
We think probably only Peter was 20 years old or older
because only Peter and Jesus had to pay the temple tax.
So Paul, now he's 30 years old, and he meets Jesus,
and this changes the entire course of his life.
As he goes on then, we see he not only encountered Christ,
but he then experienced God's grace in community.
As he goes to the city of Damascus,
there this guy named Ananias greets him and prays for him
that the scales would fall off his eyes and his sight would be restored.
He is welcomed into the community of the early church there in Damascus,
and the same people that he went there to arrest
and to carry back to Jerusalem in chains
now are welcoming him, embracing him,
protecting him, providing for him.
He experiences that grace
that even though he came there as their enemy,
they embrace him as a brother.
And as things continue,
we then see that he goes out
for a season of isolation in Arabia for three years.
And so just as Jesus' earthly disciples
got to spend three years with him doing ministry,
Paul gets to go do that out in the desert,
just communing with Jesus,
getting to know him, hearing from him,
learning more of him, all of that kind of stuff.
he gets to do all of that.
And then we find out he eventually goes to Jerusalem
where he is mentored and encouraged by Barnabas.
And then he began to serve and use his gifts in Antioch.
We talked about that last week.
And it's at Antioch where ultimately he is sent out
to reach the nations.
That, by the way, by the time we get to there in Antioch,
what we covered last week, that was at about 47 AD.
By that time, he is probably in his early 40s
by the time he goes on his first missions trip, okay?
Some of you, you've already been on a missions trip
and you're like much younger than that.
Some of you are a little older
and you're like, oh, I could never do that.
Turn to someone next to you and say,
it's never, you're never too old to go.
All right?
So from this point forward,
Saul was known as Paul.
Okay, Saul is known as Paul now.
And he can now look back on his life.
And by the way, I mentioned Paul,
while he's in this same prison cell,
he writes Ephesians as well as at the same time
he writes Philippians.
Many of you know by this time,
he is able to look back on the story of his life
and how God's will was accomplished in his life,
and he is able to say,
whatever gain I had,
I counted as loss for the sake of Christ.
All those things I was pursuing,
all my own achievements,
all the degree that I could hang on my wall,
the admiration of people around me,
the success that I experienced,
he said, everything I count as loss
for the sake of following Christ.
And all of this he's able to look at and say
this is by the will of God.
That's a consistent theme.
You see it repeated in other letters to Corinth and Colossae
and to Timothy, his apprentice.
He talks about this happened by the will of God.
This is how it all played out.
Paul saw the will of God in the story of his life,
his conversion, his spiritual growth,
his gifts, his calling, his suffering, all of that.
And as we look at that for him,
again, we're invited to pull back
and ask for ourselves, do we see the will of God in our lives?
Do we see how God's will is playing out?
Do we see how different things come together?
And whether it's the good things that we've been blessed with
or even the challenging things that we go through,
that God is able to use all of that to accomplish his will and purpose.
This is something that I think for many of us we're going to have to really wrestle with
as we go through this coming year trying to discover the higher calling that God has for us.
And there's this big idea that maybe we want to think about, explore, dig into, this idea
of the sovereignty of God, that God is the one who is actually ultimately in control
of all things.
And how does God's sovereignty work out?
How does God's will work out?
Well, it works out both in the things that he ordains and in the things that he redeems.
What do those words mean?
Ordain, redeem, those are weird words.
What do we mean by that?
When we say that God ordains something, it means that God causes it to be.
that God makes things happen.
God puts things in place.
God orders the events of our lives.
He intervenes in situations.
He arranges meetings with people.
He performs miracles.
He gives us the breath of life
that we actually live by each day.
God makes things happen.
That's what we mean when we say God ordains something.
But also God doesn't just ordain, God redeems.
Because there are a lot of other things in this world
that are very broken.
And when we say God redeems,
It means he is able to take all of those broken things.
He is able to take our sin and rebellion against God.
He's able to take our failures and mistakes.
He's able to take our foolish decisions.
He's able to take our rebellion.
He's able to take our disobedience.
He's able to take our betrayals of God.
He's able to take our deception.
He's able to take all of that.
And somehow, because of his great wisdom and great power,
he is able to redeem those and take those broken things
and make something beautiful out of them.
This is why, like in Genesis chapter 50,
Joseph is able to tell his brothers
that you meant evil against me,
but God meant it for good.
I really believe that we need to have a high view
of the sovereignty of God
as we pursue his higher calling for our lives
because think about Paul's story for a second.
He had to trust God,
not just when he's seeing miracles happen,
not just when the dead are coming to life before his eyes,
not just when demons run fleeing from him, not just when the sick are healed, not just when people
appreciate him and are thankful to him and embrace his message, but he has to trust God
even when he is being rejected and even when people are throwing stones at his head and even
when he is being beaten with rods and even when he went to be executed, he has to trust God that
this is all part of God's will and purpose for his life that's ultimately for God's glory and for his
good. Can I ask us, when I ask the question, do we see the will of God in our lives? Are we able to
trust God with everything that we're going through? The blessings that we can celebrate and even the
struggles, the questions that maybe have no answer right now that we can't fully understand. Can we
trust God that way. And just as God worked in Paul's life to lead him to the higher calling he
was created and redeemed for, I believe the Lord also works in our lives to accomplish his will
and purpose. That's why after we meet Paul here and see a bit of how God's story is playing out
in his life, we then get to see just the beginning of what we're going to be hearing about in this
letter to the Ephesians as Paul addresses it to the saints. To the saints. I know for many of us,
okay, well, what does that mean as well? Just so you know, the words, the saints, that's just the
Greek words, hoi hagioi, that means holy ones, or persons who belong to God, God's people, or saints.
And this does not mean people who are especially sanctified, people who are especially, like, really
holy people. These aren't people who are especially obedient to God. These are just people
who belong to God.
That's what it's about.
It's about people who belong to God.
And in that case, if we're reading this,
we hear this to the saints,
it's not just written to a special small group of people,
it's actually written to all of us.
But that can be hard to embrace.
Because I think for a lot of us,
when we hear the word saint,
maybe we think of an image something like this one.
We think of maybe some ladies and some dudes
and they got these cool, colorful robes on.
with a nice like roughly fringe
and they got that cool like gold halo around their heads
and maybe we just look at that
and we think, well, I'm not that.
Like that's not me.
I'm definitely not like that.
Like if someone was handing out gold halos at church,
I miss that day.
And like I'm not that.
And so we categorize ourselves as something different
and something less than, don't we?
we start to kind of diminish what God might do in our lives.
But think about this for a second.
I mean, you're likely to see images like this, stained glass windows, paintings, things like this.
You're likely to see that in church traditions like Roman Catholicism or Eastern Orthodox or things like that.
And if you ask someone in those traditions what it means to be a saint,
well, they will say something like, well, a saint is someone who is in full communion and close relationship with God.
And a saint is someone who lived a life of heroic faith and trust and bold obedience to God
and what God wanted them to do.
And a saint is someone who is a powerful intercessor,
who can ask God to do miraculous things, and God answers them.
And a saint is someone who is an example of true Christian virtue in all of their life.
That's who a saint is.
And here's the thing, brothers and sisters.
As we think about that, what we need to understand is that our brothers and sisters in the Roman
Catholic and Orthodox traditions, they don't get it wrong.
The issue is that's not just for a small, select, elite group of people.
That's the calling for all of us.
It's not just for a few.
We need, if we're going to even be able to understand and embrace everything we're going
to learn in this letter to the Ephesians, we need to realize when it says to the saints,
that means you.
That means me.
So turn to someone next to you and say, that means you.
This is for all of us.
And so for, you know, I mentioned earlier that idea with higher calling to rise above temporary pursuits to pursue God's eternal purpose.
For some of us, there are a lot of things we need to rise above.
I think we need to rise above those temporary pursuits.
But really for many of us, one thing we need to rise above is we need to rise above a low view of normal Christian life.
We have such low expectations.
We have such low expectations for ourselves.
We have such low expectations for what God could do in your life or my life,
what could happen here in our church family.
We have such little faith in what God can do.
We say, okay, maybe God's going to do something special.
Maybe God's going to do something great, but he definitely can't use me.
He definitely isn't going to work in my life group or in my church that way.
Brothers and sisters, if we're going to learn anything from this,
we have to realize this is God's calling for all of us.
And so some things we're going to talk about this year,
I'll just lay out very quickly for us.
We need to really recognize every believer is called.
And there are a lot of things we're going to talk about.
I'll just share three areas for us real quick here this morning
as we're going to go through a lot of these in Ephesians.
But one thing we need to know we're called to
is every believer is called to a relationship with God
that is life-giving, that is intimate,
that actually blesses and builds us up.
Every one of us is called to that kind of relationship with God.
And as we go through Ephesians, especially these first two chapters are going to be key.
What we really want to do is get very confident in our identity in Jesus Christ
and really bold in our understanding of the gospel
and knowing that the gospel is powerful to transform our lives
and make that relationship with God possible.
This is what we want to explore as we go into this year.
And by the way, we're going to be going through Ephesians here on Sundays,
but then we're going to follow up on that in our life groups
because it's not just hearing here from a stage from somebody, some guy up here preaching about
things. We need to be in community, wrestling with those truths, wrestling with those teachings,
praying together, asking questions together, living it out together. So we're going to be
doing that throughout this year, really pursuing that kind of close relationship with God. But
we're also called to a life of faith. And this is huge, not just a close relationship, but a life
of faith. What do I mean by that? I really think God wants us to be people, like Apostle Paul,
that as we see what it is that God is doing, that we're ready to say yes and join him. This really
requires a kind of intimate, dynamic relationship with God that leads us to taking practical steps
of faith every day. Now, there are some specific things we're going to do this year to actually
provide opportunities for our church to grow in this. There are a lot of different ways we can see
it, but one specific thing we're going to be doing is we normally have these gatherings on Friday
nights called Encounter. That's for our college students specifically, but what we're going to do
starting at the end of October is we're going to use those Friday night gatherings and open
Encounter up to anyone in our church who wants to come, and we're going to go through a curriculum
called Experiencing God Together. And just going through learning the ideas isn't going to do
something by itself, but going through this, this is a really helpful curriculum that describes the
kind of dynamic relationship with God that we're intended to live in to say, God, what are you
doing? What are you speaking? How are you leading? And God, how can I respond with a life of active
faith? So we'll talk more about this as we get closer to it, but just want to let you know this,
give you a heads up. So maybe some of you, you're like, really like to plan ahead. You can put it
on your calendars. That's great. It's going to be these Friday nights at 7 p.m. But as we go through
this, my prayer, my deep desire for our church is that we would be people who aren't just kind
of passively sitting back, maybe just kind of sitting here on a Sunday and like, okay, I've
gone through the motions and I go on my way. But people that can really relate with God, hear him
speaking, know that he is working in our lives, and respond to that with steps of faith. Actually,
if I could share a picture of this with you. Some of you, maybe this idea of like being on a diving
board, okay? I shared this with our leaders a few weeks ago because I feel like it's something that
God was speaking to me about. Some of you know I have aphantasia, meaning I can't visualize things
in my head. And so if I ever have this sense that I'm like seeing like a picture, I usually pay
attention because I feel like it's probably significant. And I remember as a number of weeks
ago, I was praying for our church. I was actually praying over this theme of higher calling. And as I
was praying, I felt like I kind of saw this thing. It's a very weird experience for me. I don't
usually do that. But it was this picture of a young child kind of on the end of a diving board
and dad's down in the pool waiting for the little kid to jump in. I'm sure many of this, if you've
been around in the church for a while, you've probably even heard of this kind of picture
as an illustration of faith of like, oh yeah, you got to kind of take the jump and dive in.
I may have heard that before. What I saw in this picture was the little kid out at the end of the
diving board, dad's in the pool saying, hey, it's okay, jump in. And the little kid turns around
and walks back off the diving board. And I felt like as I was praying, I felt like what the Lord
was showing me was, Pete, this is where you and your church are at right now. That if I call you
to jump, if I call you to take a step of faith, that you're likely to just turn around and go the
other direction entirely. But then as I was praying and I was just kind of talking through
that with God, I felt like on the other side of the pool, I saw another picture of this. And in
that picture, the kid came to the end of the diving board, jumped in the pool, dad catches him, splashes,
laughing, fun, and then another kid comes behind. And the kid already in the pool beckons that other
kid, hey, jump in. This is great. This is great. Let's do it together. And I felt like God was
saying, that's who your church is going to be. That's who your church is going to be. This is
the kind of life of faith and the challenge of it I think many of us are going to need to go through.
Say the Christian life is not just about sitting in a seat on a Sunday morning, but it's about
living in this kind of dynamic relationship with God where we're actively living out our faith in
community together. And last thing that I'll share here about this calling that we have is just that
we're called to a ministry and realizing that for each one of us, God wants us to discover our
spiritual gifts, to build up the body of Christ, to reach out to the world around us, even to be
equipped in things like prayer ministry, stuff like that, because God has a greater purpose for
our lives. And we're going to do some specific things to try to encourage and create space for
this as we go through the year. I'm not going to get into all of that right now, but as we look
ahead, I would encourage you, maybe think about what are some tangible steps I could take to
actually discover the ministry that God has for me. And by the way, just so you know, in sequence
of things, you don't discover your gifts and then serve God. You start serving God, and as you serve
God, you discover your gifts, okay? That's how that works. So I want to encourage you, like, find those
ways to start serving, and in that, you will discover the ministry and the calling that God has
for you. We'll be able to celebrate that together. As we think about all of this, okay, that's verse
one. Okay, don't worry. Verse two, we're pretty much done. Grace to you. Verse two is grace to you
and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.
On the one hand, this is a simple greeting.
You see it in a lot of Paul's letters,
a lot of other letters in the early church.
But as we think about having a higher calling in our lives,
we need to realize that we need God's grace to do that.
And God's grace is first and foremost
the grace that gives forgiveness of sin
and salvation and eternal life.
As we believe, as we're gonna remember today
as we take communion together,
that Christ laid down his life for us for our cleansing, for our healing, for our forgiveness,
for our restoration, so that we can have a relationship with God, so that we can live
in his eternal kingdom. That is the first thing, but also as we even look through the story of
Paul's life and think about what God's doing in our lives today, we need to recognize it's all
grace. It's all grace. Encountering Christ, experiencing the truth and love and community,
joining in ministry and missions, discovering our calling, all of that is the grace of God in our
lives. And it's a process that each one of us needs to go through to see, God, this is how you're
working in me and in my church family. And actually, as we come to a close in our time today,
I started today sharing three different movies with you. And I'll share a fourth one real quick
here that I think may illustrate this once again. Again, this may be a little bit older,
but some of you may have seen newer iterations.
How many of you watched The Incredibles?
Came out in 2004, right?
And if you didn't see that,
you probably saw Incredibles 2.
I think that was 2018.
And I heard Incredibles 3 is coming out in 2028.
Okay, so we can all look forward to that together.
Yeah, some of you are excited.
At least Solomon's excited, okay.
If you look at this story,
and maybe go watch the movie if you want.
Bob Parr, also known as Mr. Incredible,
can see him there in the middle.
He is a superhero, supernatural strength, right?
And he is forced into a government relocation program to hide his identity.
And he spends his days wedged inside this little cubicle at an insurance company.
And he spends eight hours a day denying insurance claims to needy clients
while enduring this kind of tyrannical and bureaucratic boss.
And it's like this horrible existence.
And he commutes every day in this tiny little car that he squeezes into.
and he eats dinner with his family in tense silence
and he lives under this mandate to try to blend in
and for his family, he and his family to be average,
to be average, to be normal.
And so he and his wife and his kids,
they're just trying to blend in
and pretend there's nothing different about them.
But Bob always wants something more than this.
What happens as the film goes on
is that he meets this woman named Mirage.
Should be a little warning there, right?
mirage approaches him to do some secret hero work on a remote island and he thinks he's found his
purpose again but this offer is actually a trap built on nostalgia and vanity playing on the fact
that bob really wants to relive his glory days from back when he was young and single and could
do it all on his own this and this ends up being a trap that almost gets him and his family killed
because of his vanity and desire to relive the glory days.
What ends up happening by the end
is that Bob realizes that his purpose
isn't about solo heroics.
It's found in protecting, equipping,
and fighting side by side with his family.
And that mundane domestic sphere
he was trying to escape from
wasn't an obstacle to his calling.
It was actually the arena
where his true calling was lived out.
And again, these movies do well
because they speak to our human condition.
And I wonder for some of us,
maybe we've been going through life
and trying to make something of ourselves,
trying to pursue the narrative
that the culture around us tells us
is gonna give us a full life,
and maybe we're realizing that it's empty,
that it's meaningless, it's chasing the wind.
Maybe today, God is trying to get our attention.
So the answer isn't just to escape
or even try to just make something of yourself.
The answer is actually to see and hear
the higher calling that God has for each one of us,
and not just to do that individually,
but actually to do that together as a spiritual family.
Again, that idea, that higher calling,
to rise above temporary pursuits,
to live for God's eternal purpose.
This is what we want to journey into this year,
and I'm just thinking, what could it look like
to explore this higher calling
as a spiritual family together?
This starts here today as we begin the process.
And as we start and before we even get ready to take communion,
I want to just give us some things to reflect and pray about
as we wrap up our time here today.
The first question I want to ask us to reflect and pray about today is,
what do you need to rise above in order to live for God's purposes?
What do you need to rise above?
And maybe that's simply a temporary pursuit.
Maybe you have been just trying to make something of yourself,
trying to earn people's approval,
trying to earn your own glory,
trying to prove yourself to the world.
Maybe you've been trying to pursue different idols,
thinking that these are the things
that are gonna fulfill and satisfy.
Maybe you need to rise above that.
Maybe it's also, like I mentioned earlier,
rising above a low view of normal Christian life.
Stop putting yourself in a different category
than those saints, those heroes of the faith,
and realize that that's your calling too.
So what do you need to rise above?
A second question I would ask you is,
how do you see the will of God at work in your life?
I think for a lot of us to really embrace
God's calling for us,
we're actually gonna need to process our past.
We're gonna need to bring that to God
and be able to celebrate the great things,
the victories, the blessings, the answered prayers,
all those kind of stuff.
We need to celebrate that,
but we also maybe need to deal with
some of the broken things,
some of the things that we need to ask God to redeem,
and maybe even surrendering to God,
some things that maybe don't have answers
right now in this present life.
But can we see the will of God
playing out in our lives,
in our sovereign foundations,
in the different experiences he's brought us through,
in the different gifts that we start to see developing?
Can we see the will of God in our lives?
And then thirdly, lastly,
who is God calling you to be?
For many of us, this is actually a hard question
to answer still, and that's okay.
A lot of us here in this room, we're very young.
A lot of us, we're still trying to discover
the unique calling God has for us.
One thing I want to be clear,
not every one of us are called to be the Apostle Paul.
That's not all of our calling.
We aren't meant to be carbon copies of him
or of one another or anybody else.
God has a unique calling for each one of us.
What might your unique calling be?
Who is God calling you to become?
And even as we reflect on Paul's story,
it might cause us to think about that
because we see the importance
of different people along the way.
Like, have you thought about this?
Paul wouldn't be Paul without his parents who raised him.
Some of you here in this room,
you're parents, you're raising your kids,
you're like, man, I'm changing the diapers.
I'm just chasing him around the house.
I'm trying to clean him up.
I'm trying to help him get ready for school,
trying to help with the last minute project.
Oh my gosh.
Can you realize God has a purpose for you
in that role as a parent?
Have you thought about that Paul wouldn't be Paul
without Gamaliel who taught him?
Some of you have a heart to teach,
to invest in the next generation.
That's so huge.
That's valuable.
That's important.
Paul wouldn't be Paul without Stephen,
the guy who testified in the streets of Jerusalem
and even at the threat to his own life
wouldn't back down.
That Paul not only condemned him to death
but sat and watched him
as he died for his faith in Christ.
Paul wouldn't be Paul without seeing that.
Paul wouldn't be Paul without Ananias
who came to Paul at a moment of crisis
and prayed for him to receive his sight.
Paul wouldn't be Paul without Ananias coming and praying for him
Paul wouldn't be Paul without Barnabas
coming and taking him under his wing
mentoring him, encouraging him
Paul wouldn't be Paul without Timothy
the apprentice who came after him
and continued his ministry
each of us here has our own
calling that's valuable in the kingdom
of God and as we pray about that
explore that, discover that this coming year
I believe that God will lead us to take bold steps of faith
together in our church family
and see what it is that God will do
As we wrap up our time here today,
what I want to point out
is that all of this started for Paul.
The pivot point was when he met Jesus for himself.
And I think it's really appropriate
that as we finish this time,
as we respond to the Lord,
that we actually do so by taking communion together
and remembering Christ
and remembering what he's done in our lives.
And so if you will,
can we take a moment and bow our heads together
and we'll prepare to take communion in this moment?